# Robert L. Anderson, II.

3068 Schubert Drive - Silver Spring, MD 20904 240.462.5173 - RobertLAndersonJunior@gmail.com

## **EXECUTIVE PROFILE**

Robert brings twenty-four years of experience as a SAS Technical Consultant specializing in advanced analytics, including seventeen years as Senior Technical Consulting Business Manager. He has driven customer implementations in a multitude of industries, including professional sports, government, education, healthcare, retail and manufacturing. Robert has a depth of knowledge in business intelligence and a wealth of experience in advanced analytics, data preparation and custom web application development. Robert's team-first management style allows him to lead organizations, as well as be a productive team member implementing others' visions.

# SAMPLING OF ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Extensive contributions to the presales effort of a multiyear contract for software and services for an international monetary organization.
- Decades of implementation experience with in diverse business sectors including Healthcare, Government, Education, Finance, Retail and Manufacturing.
- Running the day to day operations of a large consulting department with a dozen direct reports and a \$3M annual services target.

# **CORE COMPETENCIES**

- Extensive knowledge of business intelligence and advanced analytics
- Initiation, staffing and delivery of implementation services contracts
- Management and career development of an 11-member team of consultants
- Authoring of best practices for project delivery and technical functionality
- Creation of packaged services collateral

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Senior Technical Consulting Manager - January 2008 to Present

SAS Institute, Inc. – Rockville, MD – Global Hosting and US Professional Services - Business Intelligence Practice

- Specializes in Visual Analytics, Business Intelligence and custom web application development
- Manages 11-member project implementation team responsible for \$3M in annual revenue
- Delivers technical implementations and assessments with a focus on Business Intelligence
- Assigns and allocates resources for technological implementations
- Responsible for training plans, mentoring and career development of Jr. Consultants
- Works closely with sales management to position strategic services opportunities
- Creates packaged fixed price and standard time & materials service offerings for presales
- Responsible for balancing internal resource utilization with 3rd party partner assignments
- Manages internal blogs and technical resource repositories to ensure knowledge sharing
- Reviews and crafts responses to presales services proposals
- Interviews and qualifies 3rd party consultants for use on projects
- Assists with on-campus interviews and associated recruitment activities

# Technical Consultant Manager and Supervisor - December 2002 – December 2007

SAS Institute, Inc. – Rockville, MD – PSD - State and Local Government Operations

- Ran day-to-day operations of state and local government delivery team with a \$7.5M annual services target
- Created off the shelf service packaged offerings for presales teams
- Worked closely with sales management to position strategic services implementations
- Responsible for recruiting, interviewing, hiring and onboarding new consultants
- Collaborated with vertical teams to develop best practices for project implementations

# **Systems Engineer** - January 2000 – November 2002

SAS Institute, Inc. – Rockville, MD – Sales and Marketing Public Sector Group

- Responsible for programming, testing, documentation, and related tasks for technology pilot implementations
- Conducted technological assessments and drafted statements of work for pilot implementations
- Served as technical lead, determining technical specifications, resource allocation and client interaction
- Assisted sales representatives with technical insight on site visits to help influence software sales
- Conferred with management as needed to develop best practices for project delivery

# **Applications Developer** - January 1996 – December 1999

SAS Institute Inc. - Rockville, MD - Integrated Solutions Group

- Responsible for coding modules of customized SAS Applications for client solutions
- Formulated test plans and performed Quality Assurance (QA) testing for custom software applications
- Documented the requirements gathering, design, development, and quality assurance (QA) phases
- Assisted with development of project requirements and design
- Regularly interacted with clients to provide feedback and support during development phases

#### **EDUCATION**

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science - North Carolina Agricultural & Technical State University - Fall 1995